http://youtu.be/0l4bX4LxeKc
Tung Dinh_VGU http://youtu.be/0l4bX4LxeKc
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Hi.
Chào các bạn!
In this video, we will introduce digital logic--
Trong video này, ta sẽ học về digital logic
not to teach you everything about it, but give you a glimpse
Không phải tất tần tật, chỉ là khái quát
of how things work.
về cách thức làm việc
In digital logic, we have two states.
Trong digital logic, ta có 2 trạng thái
The true state is going to be mapped to a high voltage--
True tương ứng với high voltage
in our case, 3.3 volts--
trường hợp này là 3.3V
and a false state is going to be mapped to 0 volts.
False tương ứng với 0V
And the way this is going to work is around two transistors.
Cách thức hoạt động thì dựa trên 2 transistors
The first is a P-channel.
Cái đầu tiên là P-Channel
The P-channel has three pins, it has a gate, it has a source,
P-Channel có 3 chân, gate, source
and it has a drain.
và drain
And the way the P-channel works is, if there is a positive voltage--
Hoạt động như sau: nếu hiệu điện thế dương
a positive voltage--
a positive voltage--
between the source down to the gate, then this transistor will be on, and
giữa source và gate, transistor sẽ dẫn
can conduct current down, from source to drain.
và dòng điện chạy từ source tới drain
The other type of transistor also has three pins.
cái transistor kia cũng có 3 chân
It's called an N-channel.
gọi là N-Channel
And the N-channel has a gate.
N-Channel cũng có gate
And this one's the drain.
drain
And this one's the source.
và source
But it works differently.
Nhưng cách thức hoạt động lại khác
In the N-channel, a positive voltage between the gate and the source will
Trong N-Channel, hiệu điện thế dương giữa gate và source
turn the N-channel on.
làm N-Channel dẫn
But now the current will go in this direction, from drain to source.
Dòng điện chạy từ drain tới source
And what we're going to do is to combine these two
Giờ thì ta kết hợp 2 transistors này
transistors to make a gate.
để tạo 1 gate
And the first one we're going to build is an NOT gate.
Đầu tiên là NOT gate
The NOT gate has an input, which can be True or False, and an output, which
Input của NOT gate là True hoặc False,
is the opposite.
và output thì ngược lại
So True goes to False, and False goes to True.
True thành False và False thành True
And the way we're going to build it is we're going to tie the two gates
Để tạo NOT gate, ta nối 2 gate
together here.
như thế này
And that will be our input.
và nó là input
And we're going to tie the two drains together here.
ta cũng nối 2 drain lại thế này
And that will be our output.
trở thành output
And then, we're going to tie this source, here, to 3.3 volts.
rồi, source, nối với 3.3V
And we're going to tie this one to ground.
ta nối chân này với ground
Now let's see how it works.
Giờ coi nó hoạt động
If the input were True, OK-- so if the input were True--
Nếu input là True,
that means it is 3.3 volts.
tức là 3.3V
And that will create--
And that will create--
across this transistor, you'll see there's 3.3 volts in this direction.
ở transistor này, cũng là 3.3V
And this transistor will then become on.
và transistor này dẫn
But over here, we see we've got 3.3 volts to 3.3 volts.
nhưng ở đây, 3.3V tới 3.3V
And so there's no voltage across the source gate of the P. And this one
coi như 0V từ source của P-Channel
will be off.
và nó sẽ tắt
And if this transistor's off, and that one's on, we can see--
Nếu transistor này tắt, và cái này dẫn
there's 0 volts--
Ở đây 0V
that becomes 0 volts.
Ở đây cũng thành 0V
The other case is also easy to see.
Dễ thấy ở trường hợp còn lại
Now if the input were False, that means there'd be 0 volts here.
nếu input là False, tức là 0V ở đây
And on the N-channel, we have 0 volts to 0 volts, which is no drop.
Ở N-Channel, 0V tới 0V
And so this one will go off.
coi như cái này tắt
But over here, we have 3.3 volts down to 0 volts.
Nhưng ở đây, 3.3V tới 0V
And so we see a positive voltage between the source
tạo ra hiệu điện thế dương giữa source
and gate of the P-channel.
và gate của P-Channel
And it will come on and conduct.
thì nó sẽ dẫn
So if this transistor is on, and conducts, this 3.3 volts shows up at
và nếu transistor này nó dẫn
the output as 3.3 volts.
output sẽ là 3.3V
And there you have it.
như thế đấy
True goes to False, and False goes to True.
True thành False và False thành True
And this is just a glimpse of how digital logic
Đây chỉ là khái quát về digital logic
works inside the computer.
bên trong máy tính